this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Jeff Doolittle in
this episode I will be discussing
decoupled content management systems
with Bob Sheppard bob is a lead
architect at media current a single
source digital agency for development
design strategy and training he
specializes in content management
systems and web presence for major
corporations governments and nonprofits
bob is a frequent speaker at drupal
conferences and related events he is the
creator of the weekly drop an email list
that reaches over 12,000 developers in
the drupal community every week
bob is a co-organizer of the annual
decoupled day's conference in New York
and has been at the forefront of a
movement toward adoption of decoupled
content management systems which is our
topic for this episode welcome to
software engineering radio Bob thanks
Jeff it's really good to be a guest yeah
glad you could be here to join me today
so let's get started can you briefly
define content management systems for me
before we begin a deeper discussion of
what decoupled content management
systems entail yeah content management
systems have been around much longer
than I've been working in this industry
and today when you think of a content
management system most people think of
things like site core or Drupal or
WordPress and these systems are
basically software systems that allow a
team to manage the content for the
organization that could be their blog
that could be their mobile apps could be
a whole network of websites that consume
content from the content management
system they usually also handle media so
give the editors a way to create images
and upload videos and have those those
all kind of blended together into the
content we get when we go onto the web
or when we open apps so there there's a
lot of things and a lot of different
ways that they are used but that's kind
of the summary of what they are okay so
explain to me a little bit about the
trade-offs with any decision there's
always going to be pros and cons or cost
and benefits so are there any specific
challenges involved in adopting a CMS
and how does that relate to the the
trade-offs of adopting a content
management system yeah so there's a lot
of trade-offs and depending on your
needs you might choose a different
system versus another one one of the big
differentiators I think is the size of
the organization and the amount of
administrators and editors you need if
you're just starting up a blog and you
just have one or two people you know
WordPress probably is the most popular
content management system on the
Internet as far as that goes just sheer
numbers but well the vast majority of
those sites are blogs a lot of them you
know single editor blogs when you get
into more advanced requirements where
you need to tag content and you need to
have revision and kind of complex
workflows so although WordPress can do
those types of things a lot of people
will lean towards more towards something
like Drupal and and I work mostly in the
100% in the open-source world so I don't
really deal with the proprietary systems
that are out there like from Adobe and
and other companies but that's another
big differentiator a lot of people have
their options open so they like going
with open-source because you're not
locked into one vendor or they're their
product lifecycle you can customize and
and add on your own functionality and
both Drupal and WordPress give you a lot
of options there okay options are kind
of endless when it comes to that stuff
but these different systems have
different strengths and weaknesses so
absolutely so to kind of summarize what
you said there it sounds like the more
complex your requirements are or the
more collaboration that there is going
on the content management systems are
meant to kind of address those needs yes
yeah and and then you have multiple
channel content aggregation that type
those types of things if you
if you have needs there content
management systems usually a good idea
it sounds like we could deep dive into
that but we're gonna run out of time get
into decoupled content management
systems yeah so maybe let's switch gears
there now that we've sort of laid a
basic foundation of what content
management systems are all about and
what they're good for
so we're going to talk about decoupled
content management systems but first
should software engineers be interested
in content management systems I
sometimes wonder if people have the
impression maybe those are for designers
rather than engineers or architects so
in in other words why should we care
yeah it's a good question to ask because
I really do run up against that one I'm
in kind of the developer world outside
of my own typical circles when I get
around software architects that don't
work in WordPress or Drupal or in
content management systems at all yeah
there's there's this kind of idea
they're like well it's just a utility
kind of a solved problem maybe or not an
interesting problem I definitely think
there's a big place for engineers and
software architects in the CMS world and
there's a lot of them that work in this
world it may not be what's getting a lot
of the press or the attention but it's
definitely a use case there there's a
lot of complexity around delivering a
good experience to end-users but that is
more of a front-end developer problem
but there's a lot of a lot of work to be
done around the whole editorial
experience and ap is and how things
interact with each other so there's some
interesting problems to solve with with
content management systems for sure
I see so how else is the space growing
in complexity you mentioned the
front-end but I imagine cloud
technologies cloud native solutions
things of that nature might be expanding
the complexity that it takes in order to
deploy and leverage a content management
system yeah I mean you have so content
delivery networks CD ends are just kind
of an expectation these days so
WordPress Drupal all these CMS is pretty
much support that integrating with these
cloud services so you know what you're
seeing is a lot of these traditional
CMS's are adapting to meet the needs of
the market and we're where those
problems are better solved outside of
the content
system a lot of people use those
solutions
I mean Drupal has been around for a long
time as as WordPress has and a lot of
these things didn't exist when they were
originally created so there's another
aspect to it that both of these CMS's
specifically and I'm going to talk a lot
about those two because I know them the
best but you know you've got they were
created in a different time than we're
in now so there is a lot of thought
process going and like how do we what we
do if we built a CMS you know from
scratch today and how would that be
different and then trying to move these
systems to being more like like data
that approach okay so let's transition
now to talking about decoupled content
management systems specifically so how
do they differ from more the standard
coupled approach that we've had
historically yeah so a typical CMS like
WordPress or Drupal we we refer to them
now as monolithic application so they do
everything from the content editing
experience to actually writing out the
HTML and CSS that is delivered to a user
and it decoupled system differs from
that and that there are different types
of ways ways that you can decouple the
system's but basically what you're doing
is splitting apart the content
management from the actual website so
instead of instead of WordPress or
Drupal rendering HTML CSS and JavaScript
that a person actually looks at in their
browser what you're actually giving or
putting outputting from the content
management system is an API and then you
build whatever website you want so you
could build it in react or angular you
could write it in Ruby whatever system
you want to just build your website and
you interact with an API to get your
content content into the website and
that's that's the main difference
I see so so in a standard monolithic
system you might call that more of a
turnkey approach where as it sounds like
with the decoupled content management
system you're going to be putting the
pieces together and making decisions of
your own instead of having those
decisions being pre-made for you exactly
yeah like with Drupal and in WordPress
you you have to learn how to build a
theme in WordPress or Drupal and that is
going to be written in PHP you know
there are templating you know languages
and things like that that you have to
learn so it does it does make those
choices for UsWe more opinionated okay
so is there a general industry shift in
this direction or maybe is it momentum
just in certain pockets and if so kind
of what's driving this this movement
there's definitely an industry-wide
shift and there are many drivers I would
say one of them is just speed to market
and the the second one I think is the
availability of people to actually do
the front-end development the front-end
development world has rapidly adopted
JavaScript as a language and many
different tool the tooling around
javascript has just exploded in
popularity and diversity so there's all
kinds of stuff there so it's not it's
not difficult to find a good JavaScript
developer these days that can do
front-end development it's much more
difficult to find a really experienced
Drupal front-end developer that knows
Twigg which is the templating engine
that Drupal uses and so the WordPress I
think it's a little bit they have a
simpler system but it's still you know I
don't really know a lot of WordPress
developers that love that would prefer
writing their template and PHP they
prefer JavaScript I see
so the shifts in front-end technologies
are one of the drivers and it sounds
like maybe there's some other ones from
the backend as well talk a little bit
about what the nature is of decoupling
the backend system so versus separating
content entry from content delivery I
imagine there's a lot more to the
architecture behind it than just that
separation yeah there there is and
especially you know if you look at an
existing or a legacy system like
WordPress or Drupal versus something
some of the newer systems that are being
that are coming out or hosted solutions
even more so they're eight the newer
things or API driven so that's that's
their singular focus to start with and
tools like WordPress and Drupal that is
where they're moving they're developing
API first initiatives where they're
really focusing on the API level and
even internally
decoupling the systems that that you
know work with each other within the
software project so a lot of the
reasoning behind that is that these
systems have developed over years and
their complexity has gotten very high so
it is it's more and more difficult to
jump into WordPress or Drupal into the
core system and understand what's
happening and so there's a desire to
kind of break out those systems where
they can be used interchangeably and it
makes it easier to maintain the project
as a whole and I'm talking about
actually the core project not not what
somebody that's just using it would do
but just for the long-term health of the
project it needs to happen interesting
so that's an yeah that's another aspect
so even with the standard monolithic
couples content management systems it
sounds like they're moving to a
decoupled approach as well as they are
able to yeah I think the impact of you
know current martin fowler's talks and
blog posts from years and years ago
about microservices have they still are
still having impact across you know
these older systems that predated the
micro-services kind of revolution it can
be taken to an extreme that's too far
and doesn't make sense
away from monoliths but there's a lot of
lessons to be learned you know that
we've learned over the years from
software development that if you break
if you have something really really
complex it's hard to get your head
around it's really hard to maintain so
it makes sense to break things into
services and do that type of approach so
you mentioned that one of the risks is
you can over D couple so that would
definitely be a potential wrong decision
so what factors do you use to sort of
help you make that determination of how
much coupling is too much versus how
much decoupling is too much yeah the way
the way I like to look at it when I come
into a project for a client and I'm just
you know at a discovery on a project is
just to look at what are the problems
they're trying to solve here and in a
lot of cases it makes the most sense
just to use just a standard Drupal
install or standard WordPress install
because they don't need to decouple
their content from their content
management they don't need they don't
have apps they don't they don't need to
an API so
you're adding a bunch of complexity you
know for no real gain I see but you know
there are other situations where you
know they may not have a lot of apps or
API needs but they do have front-end
developers and those developers bet they
know JavaScript and they and they let's
say they want to they know react and
they want to do redesigns pretty much
every year we don't want them to have to
learn Drupal just for the content
management part of it because they could
have a pretty simple Drupal site and
it's very low maintenance or a simple
WordPress site and they can focus on new
versions of their website using the
tools they like and you know the word
the the content management can be kind
of boring it can just be a you know a
service that they use okay so let's talk
about I mentioned before that it seems
that monolithic content management
systems could be considered more turnkey
but are there any such things as turnkey
decoupled content management systems or
is someone required to put their entire
system together themselves there are
some it's I hesitate to call them
turnkey because you on almost all of
them or all huh maybe just say all of
them you have to set up your content
model so your content types fields
permissions things like that that you
need but there are some solutions both
open source and closed source for that
they're like Drupal has a distribution
which is kind of like a custom version
of Drupal called Contenta and you can
download install that and it basically
has pretty much everything you'd want
installed and enabled and configured in
good defaults and then you can go in and
set up your content types and then there
are closed source services that you can
just pay for one of them is net Liffe
ICMS there's another one called sanity
there's contentful and these are all
kind of API based content management
systems you know you can go get started
in minutes and you're not hosting
anything you're just paying for a month
either paying monthly or paying base
based on what you use so you don't have
to go out there and build your CMS you
can there's there's all kinds of
different levels of effort you could
have on the scale I say interesting so
what challenges have you faced as you've
been communicating the need for
decoupled content management systems in
certain situations I think one of the
challenges is communicating this to a
non-technical audience what what does
the editorial experience look like how
does it change and even when you try to
explain it
people seem like they're getting it but
they're they're not really getting it
until they see it so I think having
demos and things like that worries like
here's you know you're editing in one
browser window and your websites in a
different one there are different URLs
and just when you make a change and
click Save you may not show up
immediately on the actual website
depending on your configuration
you know the WYSIWYG kind of problem
that has been around for years where
what you see is what you get is what
that stands for for those that don't
live in this world and those I mean I've
spent a little good part of my career
just dealing with the hell that is
WYSIWYG they've never actually accurate
yeah so that's one challenge another one
is just you you're basically taking out
a bunch of complexity that existed in a
system and expand breaking that into
different services so if somebody
doesn't know that that complexity is
there because it's been buried away from
them inside of a monolith it can seem
like the you're adding complexity but
what you're actually doing is making you
know those complex items breaking them
into simpler systems where somebody on
your team can be an expert in them and
focus on them so the just explaining
that stuff there's just a lot of
complexity in how these systems work
together and a lot of folks that are not
engineers are not familiar with what's
actually happening there's a lot of
magic basically right so what would an
end user experience distinctly with a
well decoupled content management system
versus a coupled one before you
mentioned for example you might enter
your content and then you have another
browser window open to a different URL
in order to review the published content
you also mentioned something about a
delay which we could have a whole
conversation about eventual consistency
but let's avoid that for now but but the
way you described it it almost sound
like a drawback to the end user so
what's the positive benefit for me maybe
as a non-technical end user of a
decoupled content management system
where I would say oh I understand here's
what I'm gaining by going that route
yeah it is definitely a trade-off and I
will say that
describing it today kind of the
experience I see that there's a slight
delay or maybe a few minute delay and
that that is a problem the industry is
going after and figuring out ways to to
avoid so where it's almost instantaneous
but the trade-off there is that you get
this multiple channel content API that
you can write once and publish
everywhere that and that's been the case
that's nothing really new I mean before
we had this fancy term decoupled people
like the like NPR had content management
system that they use and they were they
were writing up stories and then
publishing them to Twitter and
publishing them to their blog publishing
to their podcast all at the same time so
that that really is like the big win is
that you can get all that content out
and the editor only has to write at once
interesting okay so let's switch gears a
little bit and talk about the challenges
that you've faced when you've tried to
implement decoupled well I shouldn't say
try but when you have successfully as
well implemented decoupled content
management systems on any particular
projects you've worked on yeah one of
the challenges I think that is the
biggest one in my mind right now is the
kind of editor experience and basically
preparing people for the difference with
what they're used to of it being two
separate systems the website and then
the content management system and
getting them to where they understand
the benefits versus just the drawbacks
and that that's kind of a challenge as
far as on the personal and the training
level but on the technical level one of
the challenges biggest challenges I've
seen is that service our projects like
WordPress and Drupal allow you to do a
whole lot of things and some of those
things they don't do R extremely well I
would say like Drupal one of Drupal's
bigger weaknesses is probably that it's
not the greatest system for building
landing pages and when I say landing
pages that's kind of a marketing term
but basically layout management and that
kind of thing so how you want the page
to be laid out and then adding in a
bunch of widgets and things like that
there are there different ways to do
that with Drupal for years it's a tough
problem to solve actually to make it
both performant easy to use and you know
low bug and you know so you don't have a
lot of bug
in your page and that any decoupled
approach is very complicated to do it's
a lot easier to do in a traditional
Drupal or WordPress site
so there are services like I always like
to look at complex problems is there are
there startups that totally focus on
this one problem and there are landing
page builder startups that are very
successful because that's all they focus
on its building a landing page right I
think that's one of the more weak spots
in the decoupled architecture is is
landing page building I mentioned some
other ones but those are those are two
really big ones right now a lot of the
other ones have kind of over the past
year and a half or two become kind of
solve problems so maybe describe to me
briefly and I know it's difficult
without pictures but what are the main
elements that somebody would have in
their decoupled architecture with this
approach and maybe name some of the
tools that you've used or that you have
exposure to that sort of fill some of
those various roles within this
decoupled system yeah for sure
so I've already mentioned Drupal and
WordPress so that's content management
there are other tools that I've used a
lot one of them being graph QL graph QL
is a query language it's basically just
a standard and there are plenty of
projects that implement that standard so
things like Apollo and there are many
other projects so basically what that
tool does is we'll take in API endpoints
from different sources and provide them
as a singular API for your team to use
so you can write queries that are very
expressive of what you need and only get
back the data that you've requested so
that that could be a whole show on graph
QL it's a great tool but that's heavily
in the in use in the JavaScript world
and it definitely in the decoupled world
so I've been able to build api's with
graph QL that would allow our front-end
developer team to just have one API they
deal with for all their content and they
write queries and they only get back the
data that they're requesting so you know
I'm sure your new listeners are all
familiar with rest and that kind of
approach graph QL is a very different
approach whereas with rest endpoints you
make a request and you get back the
whole object even if you only need a
couple of properties on the object
whereas with graph QL you can specify
that in your query I just want the title
and the slug or the URL and that's all I
want and that's all you'll get right and
so that's that's one of the tools you
don't have to use that but then we also
have things for authentication so we've
used AWS as author although all the
cloud providers have different
authentication tools things like auth0
and octa are two big names in that world
so your WordPress typically would handle
user management but you can totally
decoupled that from Drupal or WordPress
and use a service another one is search
so your search index so you could use a
patchy solar or elastic search I mean
there's literally a limitless number of
things that you can bring into a
decoupled architecture so there's more
I'm sure I could get into but yeah those
are like the big ones that we use over
and over again okay so those are some of
the those almost sound like approaches
but maybe name the tool like for example
gatsby j/s is one that I'm mildly
familiar with and my understanding is
you have some experience with that so
yeah sort of what spaces is a tool like
that filling and what isn't it providing
for you that you have to add not to it
when you want to deploy a system like
this yeah and so gatsby is a great
example in the architecture I kind of
described there where you have Drupal or
WordPress as a CMS and you've got all
these other services doing things that
you might need Gatsby was is actually
your website so it's originally was
billed as a static site generator so you
would just it would just actually build
static HTML CSS and JavaScript out and
then you could host that on any server
you know you want to you could put it on
github you could put it on a host you
could store it on your raspberry pi that
that basically build your website and
gatsby is a really popular tool that we
use a lot written in react and so it
essentially gives you a website and on
top of that you get a react application
so your website is statically rendered
when somebody comes to the website the
HTML is already rendered but also you're
loading up a react application so you
can do build time things that's all your
static stuff but you also have the
runtime of react so soon as the brow
there hits that page your react
application comes into play and you can
make queries you can dynamically change
things depending on who the user is and
things like that
I see so it sounds like there you're
trying to get the best of both worlds
between static site generation and
runtime dynamic behavior yeah yeah and
and gatsby just one of them right there
there's a lot of competitors there's
other tools that people use with
decoupled that are written in other
languages and the gatsby's with what I'm
most familiar with okay so tell us a
little bit about how you manage a
decoupled content management system so
to start with what does it look like to
test the system like this that's a
really good question in some ways it's
simpler than a monolithic approach and
in some ways it's more complicated
because you have more discrete tools and
code to deploy so you have in a way more
things that you're aware of that you
need to test so starting with the CMS
part we start with a design spec like
here's they put the API here's what we
need here's the fields that we need
represented you know Drupal is a really
good tool for building that because
there's a module built into Drupal core
now called JSON API and it's based on
the JSON API spec you can go look that
up in your own time but it's it's
basically a rest-based specification for
for content and so you you define out
what you wanted to look like and you
turn on some modules and then you can
send it through your QA department you
can generate some demo content and make
sure that you're getting back what
you're requesting when you make HTTP
requests and then for all the other API
services is very similar you can write
tests you can run it through your QA
like here's what we expect from this
input we expect this output so there's
more of a like surface area to test but
the test to me are simpler whereas with
a traditional Drupal site you're gonna
be doing a lot more testing that is more
developer specific like unit testing
type things which you can do with with
all these approaches but it's just a
little bit more discreet when it's its
own service ok or you'll be doing more
manual testing or automating it with
something like selenium versus testing
directly against API endpoints
yeah exactly those selenium was the name
I couldn't remember okay so how about
deployment what does that look like and
how important is it to be able to deploy
individual different components and
version them independently of one
another because otherwise you could get
into a situation couldn't you where you
just have a distributed monolith exactly
yeah this is this is one of the things
that's a little tricky when you first
start doing it is figuring out
deployment how do we want to handle this
in practice it hasn't been that
difficult because when I first started
doing this I was thinking we should have
more of the services in the same code
repository but I was trying to avoid was
that having all these different repos
that we have to manage and these
deployment scripts and versioning but
what turned out it turned out to be more
of a hassle than it was worth so we
broke out most of the services and to
discrete git repos and then we can
handle you know deployment with Jenkins
and and different tooling individually
but it is more complicated deployment I
think is more complicated with the
decoupled approach because you have to
know where the dependencies are where
the arrows are pointing and it does does
require more communication I think just
to make sure you're not breaking
anything on the other hand I have been
able to see on projects that because
we're decoupled our front-end team has a
lot more confidence in deploying code
changes to production during peak hours
because there's just a lot lower risk
because it's easier to rollback than a
traditional CMS because usually it's
static HTML and the api's don't change
that often because we you know done it
right and we've defined our spec ahead
of time I say in some ways it's more
complicated but I think it's more
resilient you can change one thing in a
system and not affect others but you
know when you get into API level then
you have to be a lot more careful about
what your changes and make sure they
don't have cascade down the the line of
the dependencies so what I heard there
is you've made it easier for developers
especially front-end developers to feel
confident about making changes rapidly
so they can respond very quickly if
there's a requested change but it sounds
like you also spend a
amount of time making sure that your API
endpoints are more stable and less
subject to change and it's that
foundation of stability that gives the
front-end developers that ability to
respond to change more quickly
am i hearing that correctly yeah that's
exactly what we're trying to do and in
practice I think it's shown that to be
true and it it's another advantage of
this approach is that a reason one
reason I will recommend decoupled
sometimes is if the team really wants to
iterate rapidly you know post-launch
they were building a new site and they
they don't want to be tied to the
release cycle of WordPress or Drupal
they want to be decoupled in in their in
their design so that they can make an
spin out new versions to the site
without having to touch their content
management system and anybody who's
worked in the drupal wall for a long
time will know the pain of updating from
say Drupal 6 to 7 and and Drupal as a
project has gotten a lot better about
major release changes to where now it's
kind of a rolling release system it does
give you a lot more options and more
speed to market I see so you've
mentioned Drupal a few times in our
conversation and I want to come back to
that in a minute but one more thing
before we do can you speak a little bit
to the different security related
challenges that you might have working
with a decoupled content management
system versus the standard system yeah
definitely that is another big bonus of
using decoupled on the positive side
that doesn't mean there's not risks with
doing decoupled on the security side
there definitely are but I really have
to highlight these advantages when you
have a system like a WordPress or Drupal
they've been around for a long time
and and I think both of the systems are
really secure however you are setting up
a system that's written in a scripting
language that is accessible to the world
so you have to watch out for your inputs
so if you have comments or if you have
authenticated users and they're able to
create content or anything like that you
open yourself into a sequel injection
attacks so that's what the traditional
CMS I mean all of all of them have this
problem because you have a database
that's connected to the internet so that
that is a problem that you do not have
any decoupled system because
a lot of the systems you're just gonna
have a statically generated HTML
Javascript and CSS code and there's
really nothing that can be done to
compromise that site unless the server
that it's running on is compromised but
there's no real way to do that so you
kind of get a bunch of security bonuses
like the things that are surface area of
security risks just taken off the table
because you just don't have those
vulnerabilities now that said yeah most
websites are not hundred percent static
so let's say you have to have user sign
up or something like that then you're
gonna have to have a form so your forms
gonna have to post to some API and most
api's are not open to the world so
you're gonna have to have API keys and
you don't want those just passed clear
in the clear through the browser so
right there's all kinds of challenges
there most of them are solved by having
a good API that that uses keys that
rotate or you know there's multiple you
know using cross-origin requests making
sure you're doing that right so you're
not just allowing requests to come here
mini website in the world so there's
there's a whole list of things but on
the whole I think that a couple
approaches actually more secure than say
the traditional CMS now a question on
that though it sounds like you're saying
that when you're doing decoupled content
management that inherently you're going
to do static site generation and before
you speak to that what I'm what I'm
hearing is you're basically reducing
your threat vector when you go as static
site generation because you have to
explicitly opt in to say a form being
able to be submitted or something of
that nature versus with standard content
management systems every page request is
rendered at request time yeah and
leaving you liable to attack yeah so so
the attack vector limitation makes sense
but speak a little bit to whether or not
static site generation is an inherent
and necessary part of decouple content
management systems or if that's maybe
just something you would say as a best
practice yeah thank you for calling that
out because I think it's just extremely
common and popular now for there to be
static site connected with decoupled but
those are independent things there are
plenty of decouple projects that are not
statically generated and there are
plenty of statically generated sites
that
decoupled so right yeah that's a fair
point and yeah it's complicated like
there's so many different combinations
of these things that you can do and
decoupling is a very broad term and a
lot of times that we focus on like the
headless type of niche of that which is
you know you have a CMS that doesn't
actually render HTML and then you have a
statically generated site that pulls
data from an API and that's just one one
type of the couple project I see but I'm
glad you mentioned headless content
management systems because I think
that's something that might have already
been in listeners minds up to this point
yeah you've mentioned Drupal a few times
more than a few times and I know you
have a lot of experience with Drupal and
I'm sure you'll be sharing us with us
toward the end of the podcast a little
bit about that but tell me what do you
see the future for tools and platforms
like Drupal in a decoupled world is
there a place for them in projects that
you're looking to build in the near
future or do you see them kind of
staying in this space therein but not
expanding to move more into the
decoupled space so that's a big question
but it's one I've thought a lot about so
Drupal specifically I can't speak to
WordPress as much but there has been a
lot of mindshare and resources thrown at
making sure Drupal is moving in the
right direction the direction that the
industry is going only time will tell if
it that'll be successful if it's you
know too late
I don't think Drupal is going away I'm
not trying to say that I just I don't
have a crystal ball
I think the Drupal community is doing
the right things they're focusing on
getting their API is improved and being
able to be the best open-source API
driven content management system while
not compromising on like the old
approach of just you know out of the box
you can build whatever you want so I
think that's kind of the trajectory of
the Drupal project and you know I I
still think Drupal is a really good
choice for most of the projects I ever
see and that that's probably because of
the company I work at but we it's very
well adopted in higher education in
large companies larger organism
have complex needs because of the
richness of the ecosystem around it
there's so many contributed projects
that you can piece together kind of like
Lego blocks and build whatever you need
so that that's like the real big plus in
the way of Drupal on top of on top of
the security team that the Drupal has
that stays on top of security
vulnerabilities and it's just a very
well developed team of open-source
developers that work together to make
sure that this is a good system
so maybe summarize for me again if I'm
evaluating a content management system
approach for my company what are the
factors that would help me decide you've
mentioned a few but maybe just summarize
them here for us
what are some factors that would help
you decide I really need to go with a
decoupled approach or I really need to
go with the static approach or maybe I
could choose either but I know what the
pros and cons are of each so what
factors do I absolutely want to make
sure that I'm evaluating when I'm making
a decision like this yeah this is and
this is a question I get asked a lot so
and I'm always evaluating my answer so
let me know what you think I think I
think a big factor is content
distribution single channel or multi
channel and what I mean by that is like
do you just have a website or do you
have a website and app publishing to
Twitter Instagram Facebook and is that a
problem for you would you like it to be
a single system that manages all that or
at least that option another factor I
think is your team build up who's on
your team are you supporting this
internally if so what are the tools that
they are comfortable with using if they
already are very comfortable with
front-end development tools and you want
to be able to really quickly iterate on
your design maybe it makes sense to go a
decoupled route whether that's Drupal or
not is a separate question but I think
that's one of the things we look at a
lot okay so we were talking about the
various factors I think I'm curious
about performance but I think you
already spoke to that one because static
site generator decoupled content
management systems you can have a
monolith that does static site gender
performance or end-user related factors
that might be something you want to
consider with whether you're going to go
couple
versus decoupled ya decouple approaches
just you said it early on it gives you
more choices for the system so you're
not tied into let's say PHP for your
template system or you're not tied into
server-side rendered PHP HTML you have
way more options you can write a
front-end and Python or you could write
it in an angular or react and maybe
maybe you have a bunch of people that
just came on your team that all know
react really well and you none of them
have ever used Python or PHP and you
want to move away if your systems are
decoupled you just have a lot more
options there because you can you can
change your front-end without having to
change your backend right but of course
too many options can be a bad thing -
yes that is very true like so the site's
really simple like I said early on was
like you had a simple blog and you want
to get it up this weekend you know I
wouldn't recommend unless you're a
developer and we like to do these type
of things over the weekend you know
probably you want to go with WordPress
or maybe not even WordPress maybe you
want to go with one of these hosted
blogging platforms like medium I don't
know but I think the use case is what
matters the most like what are your
goals what are your priorities maybe you
have a team full of Drupal developers
and none of them they all hate
JavaScript well I mean Indy couple
probably doesn't make a lot of sense
right but the nice thing about what's
happening in Drupal and WordPress is
that even if you're not doing decoupled
you still get all that API goodness
built in so you could render your HTML
with Drupal let let it do that job and
also feed out all that content to you
know Twitter or you know a sister site
that consumes your content so that's one
of the side benefits of all this API
driven stuff is now the tools built into
these systems are getting better and you
know more powerful yeah you kind of
expanded my mindset a bit there when you
talked about interfacing with other
third parties or applications that you
have that aren't just websites with your
content management system so let's maybe
explore that a little bit more I
understand when you post a Twitter you
post a Facebook they'll very often do a
screen scrape of an HTML page how does
that work differently when
you're having them interface with your
decoupled content management system yeah
how that happens is they they look at
them so like Twitter for example they
look at the meta tags in your HTML and
one of the beautiful things about the
Internet is that it's so anarchic and
that can be good and bad and one of the
bad things is that there's so many
varying standards so every social
provider has their own special way that
they like to have the meta tag set so to
make it work with decoupled because
there are modules in the Drupal world
that just kind of set that stuff up for
you you just have to handle that in your
front-end so you have to set up your
meta tags to display like a short
snippet and maybe you know a trimmed
version of your main profile pic or
whatever that you're using so it's it's
totally a solvable problem and I think
like Gatsby has like a built-in tool
that you can use for that stuff
interesting so the standard that Twitter
and Facebook are using to retrieve the
data is basically what they're already
doing but the decoupled approach is
making it easier for you to present the
appropriate meta tags for those
third-party systems when they scrape the
HTML page yeah this isn't really much of
a difference with decoupled or coupled
okay I mean most Drupal sites if they're
set up properly there's a module that a
co-worker of mine maintains called meta
tag and for Drupal at least and it's
used on tons and tons of sites and it
basically does this for you so it
presents it like a forum so we can get
defaults or you can override it
so one of the disadvantages of decoupled
a lot of times is especially because
it's still young still new some of these
solutions aren't as well tested and and
maybe some of them don't exist where
they do exist like in the Drupal
WordPress world so but that's another
opportunity for folks to get their feet
into open source development so it's a
kind of a you know mixed mixed bag
they're open invitation to listeners to
contribute yeah exactly
so you mentioned apps maybe speak to
that a little bit I've got an iOS app or
an Android application and I want those
to benefit from having a headless or
decoupled content management system how
could that work to help me well I mean I
think developers would rather focus on
their core product instead
of the supporting cast of services so
the benefit is that once you build this
content API you might be doing it
originally just to feed your website but
you've already now you've got this
content API so you I want to request the
most recent ten articles I can just make
an HTTP request and get that information
and now the app developer team they
don't have to go write an API or
anything they can just use the the API
that's already there for them for
content and that's that's one of the big
big pluses that people like with a
couple this you develop a content API
that and you don't have to redo that
every time you develop a new app I
imagine you could still implement that
with rest but what are the pros and cons
of either approach and are there maybe
some other approaches that somebody
could have besides those two there are
pros and cons with rest in graph QL I'm
not an expert in this this subject but
I've definitely worked with both quite a
bit and so rest is definitely the older
kid on the block been around most people
understand it so that's a that's a big
advantage it's also just baked in with
Drupal core with WordPress as well most
most developers know how to work with
with rest but the big difference between
the two is the rest the back-end
developer is defining the the Content
model 100% and the front-end or consume
it doesn't have to be front-end but I
mean the consumer of the API really
there their options are limited they can
request a resource and then they get
back whatever that resource has graph QL
is a different structure where your your
queries that you actually send a post
with the query and then the graph QL
server will respond with just the data
that you requested and so the advantage
there is that there's less data crossing
the network the consumer doesn't have to
filter out the content they do want or
they don't want which can be
embarrassing in some situations like if
you get in a situation where you're
requesting a bunch of data and some of
that data you never want to show in your
app but somebody made a bug or made a
mistake and now you're showing you know
like somebody's phone number where you
shouldn't
Graff qle if that's not in your query
you won't get the phone number back
whereas with rest you're kind of at the
mercy of the back-end team that wrote
the API and somebody could crack open
their chrome tools look at the console
and see that in transit versus in graph
QL if it's not part of the query it will
never come back across the wire at all
yeah that's it that's a good point yes
definitely one of the disadvantages of
graphic ul is that because you have that
flexibility you have to really think
about your graph QL API differently
because you can see it in situations
where a front-end developer or a client
developer the civilian a client that
consumes content could write a query
that you know could may bring bring the
server to its knees you can write really
complex things so there's a balancing
act there you're I mean they think
you're shifting more power over to the
consumer versus the power being in the
backend so a lot of us that have lived
in the back end of helping it's a little
uncomfortable at first but I do think
the benefit for us that right API is
from time to time is that this means
less revisions on the API because the
flexibility is there we don't have to
have version 15 of our REST API and
maintain all 15 versions of the API
right so it's helped it helps out a lot
there and and the front-end devs really
love love it because of the power it
gives them so okay so don't expose your
graph QL API endpoints to the public I
think is a word of caution there yes you
want to be careful what I mean with any
API yeah you need to handle handle like
I said cores you want to use JSON web
tokens I mean there's other approaches
and things but yeah you definitely want
to make sure be careful yeah
conversation possibly for another day
yes you definitely want to think about
it and do some research okay so where
should people get started it sounds like
it's a lot to swallow it's people have
been drinking from a firehose for the
about the last hour but if people want
to get started where should they go if
they want to learn more about decoupled
content management systems I've been
looking at this website it's I think is
pretty interesting if you're coming from
more of a back-end kind of perspective
called headless CMS org and I don't know
if it's geared towards back in folks
probably not but it gives you a nice
list
of different CMS's that are headless or
decoupled and there's everything on
there from Jekyll to ejecta admin which
I've never heard of to the Drupal one I
mentioned before Contenta there's an
odious one called strappy there's ghosts
and then there's there's some of the
close source kind of started up B once
like sanity and contentful I think
probably the easiest one to get started
with is something like sanity or
contentful because you can just go spin
up a site for free and get an API and to
start playing with things if you want to
get into more flexibility and you know
either note or PHP you get one of these
open source ones and install it and just
start messing around with it it's pretty
fun just to kind of play with this stuff
like you said spin it up on a weekend
because that's what developers like to
do yeah and I have to say like the the
content projects really good for drupal
you know but if you're not a PHP person
or you know comfortable with Drupal that
might not be the best place to start
okay is there anything else that we
might have missed on the topic that you
want to mention in the time we have left
I don't think so we covered a whole lot
of space there along this technology
spectrum so yeah yeah we definitely did
didn't go deep dive but a few times we
we drove down a little bit but there's a
lot of breadth here I think that people
could start digging deeper into yeah so
how can people find out more about what
you're up to you can check out I'm on
Twitter although I'm not as active as
they used to be their Shepherd on
Twitter i blog occasionally over at the
media current.com website and i co hosts
a podcast over there called open waters
and we talked to folks in the industry
and then I have a weekly drupal
newsletter that I've been doing for a
really long time called the weekly drop
com and so if you're interested in
drupal and just keeping up with that
stuff definitely recommend that yeah
there's one other thing I'm working on a
new project for developers called for
the dev comm it's just a basically a
place where you can get developer swag
t-shirts and stuff like that stickers so
that should be launching soon so if you
want to be on the email list just go on
over there and sign up it sounds great
well Bob thank you very much for this
discussion about decoupled content
management systems it's been a pleasure
thanks for having me alright this is
Jeff Dolittle for software engineering
radio thanks for listening thanks for
listening to se radio an educational
program brought to you by Triple E
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at SE - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at SC radio.com you can also
email us at team @ SC - radio net this
and all other episodes of se radio is
licensed under Creative Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening